Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE) Records
Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE) Records
1952-2007
1970-1988
Association for Continuing Higher Education (U.S.)
8.5 linear ft.
Administrative records of the adult education organization - meeting minutes (annual meetings, board of directors, committees), correspondence, directories, financial records, institutional membership files, and publications. Organizations represented include the Association of University Evening Colleges, the Adult Education Association, the Coalition of Adult Education Organizations and the Evening Student Personnel Association. Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include Frank C. Carroll and Howell McGee.
149438
Biographical History
Originally founded in 1939 as the Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC), the organization was renamed the Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE) in 1973. ACHE's membership and services encompass the entire spectrum of continuing higher education in the United States and internationally. Initially, as AUEC, it focused on the needs of administrators and faculty of evening colleges, on the assumption that quality evening college professionals lead to quality evening collegiate programs. Today, in addition to evening programs, ACHE services influence all types of continuing higher education activities. The Association membership is divided into eleven regions, each of which conduct one or more regional meetings each year, and ACHE as a whole sponsors a general annual meeting.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE) Records contains administrative and organizational files from the adult education organization. Of particular interest are the institutional membership files, which offer a unique window into the milieu of American evening colleges in the late 1960s and early 1970s.
Annual meetings contains fliers, brochures, programs, and correspondence relating to ACHE's annual meetings. Board of directors contains lists of board members, minutes from board meetings, and board correspondence. Like most large organizations, ACHE had several dozen committees in existence at any given moment; this material is located in Committee files. Since committees began, ended, merged, separated, and sometimes changed their names at various times, there is some subject matter overlap amongst the files in this series. Regions contains material related to ACHE's separate regional chapters, most from the 1960s and 1970s with a subseries devoted to the 1989 regional conferences. Correspondence comprises general organizational correspondence covering nearly thirty years while Directories covers the same time period. Financial records comprises 35 years of financial reports.
Membership in ACHE was open to any evening college, but required an application and a site visit by ACHE representatives. These reports, formally written up and submitted by the site visit team to ACHE along with their recommendation, cover a range of topics -- enrollment size, course offerings, ratio of full-time to part-time faculty, whether or not evening students had their own student council and/or student publication, registration and commencement fees, and more. Institutional membership files contains applications and reports for more than one hundred evening colleges across the United States, and provides a unique snapshot of the state of evening college programs in the mid-1960s to early 1970s.
ACHE also formed Interassociational relationships with a number of other adult education organizations, including the Adult Education Association of the USA (AEA-USA), American Council on Education, Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), Evening Student Personnel Association, International Council for Adult Education, and United States Association of Evening Students.
Publications contains material relating to ACHE's journal, Continuing Higher Education, other publications, and issues of various newsletters and news bulletins.
Miscellaneous includes background information on the organization (bylaws, constitution, statement of goals, handbook, logo development, membership survey, organizational profile), material relating to various miscellaneous topics (the 1967 Galaxy Conference, career education, the Canadian Association for University Continuing Education), and a notebook (disassembled and foldered) on the strategic planning retreat held in 1986.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Among them are the records of ACHE's predecessor organization, the Association for University Evening Colleges (AUEC), and the records of the Coalition of Adult Education Organization (CAEO). Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Carroll, Frank C.; McGee, Howell; Adult Education Association; Association for Continuing Higher Education (U.S.), Archives; Association of University Evening Colleges (U.S.); Coalition of Adult Education Organizations; Evening Student Personnel Association; Adult education; Applications.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE).
Inventory
- Annual meetings
  - Annual meetings, 1963-1988; 26 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual meetings, 1989-1990; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Board of directors
  - List of board members, 1962-1989 (Box 2)
  - Meetings
    - 1971-1990, 29 folders (Box 2)
    - 1992-2007, 6 3.25" floppy discs, MSWord files (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1979, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1983-1989 (Box 2)
- Committee files
  - Committee masters, undated (Box 2)
  - Committee lists and other information, 1971-1988 (Box 2)
  - Accreditation liaison, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Advisory, 1960-1966; 1983-1984,; 1988 (Box 2)
  - Aims and objectives, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Applications of new technology, 1984; 1988 (Box 2)
  - Awards, 1977; 1982-1989 (Box 2)
  - Budget and finance, 1988 (Box 2)
    See also Finance (Box 3)
  - Career change, 1983; 1988 (Box 2)
  - Constitution and bylaws, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Continuing education for the older adult, 1979; 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    See also Older adults (Box 4)
  - Continuing education for school personnel, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
  - Counseling, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Ethics, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Evening business programs, 1962-1965 (Box 3)
  - Executive committee, 1960-1971; 1979,; 1981,; 1983,; 1985-1989,; 2004-2007; 14 folders; 1 CD, MSWord files; CD includes strategic plan, chronology, awards, officers (Box 3)
  - Finance, 1954-1968; 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    See also Budget and finance (Box 2)
  - Future, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    See also Strategic planning (Box 4)
  - Graduate education, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Handicapped adults, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Higher adult education, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Human resource development, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Humanities, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - International continuing higher education, 1982; 1984-1985,; 1988 (Box 3)
  - Labor and education, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Legislative, 1962; 1965-1975; includes proposed amendments to Title IV, Higher Education Act of 1965 (Box 3)
    See also Title I of higher education (Box 4)
  - Legislative and legal issues, 1979; 1983-1984,; 1988 (Box 3)
  - Legislative information, 1959-1963 (Box 3)
  - Liberal education, 1958-1960; includes essay, "When is education liberal?" (Box 3)
  - Local arrangements, 1968-1979; 1985-1990; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Marketing (task force), 1987-1989; includes copy of task force findings (Box 3)
  - Membership, 1960-1966; 1978-1980,; 1988 (Box 3)
    See also Miscellaneous: Membership survey (Box 8)
  - Membership development, 1979; 1983-1988,; undated (Box 3)
    See also Public information and membership development (Box 4)
  - Membership promotion, 1965-1970 (Box 3)
  - Membership services and benefits, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Mentoring, 1982-1983; 1985,; 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Military affairs, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Minimum data and definitions (joint committee), 1960-1980; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Minorities and immigrant affairs, 1985; 1988; includes case study, "To improve the sensitivity and curricular adaptability of historically black colleges for students who must work full time" (Box 3)
  - Nominating / Nominations, 1958; 1961-1969,; 1975-1979,; 1983-1984,; 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Older adults, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
    See also Continuing education for the older adult (Box 3)
  - Organization and structure, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Program, 1963-1966; 1970-1972,; 1979,; 1983,; 1987-1989; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Public information, 1982-1984 (Box 4)
  - Public information and membership development, 1985 (Box 4)
    See also Membership development (Box 3)
  - Public relations, 1958-1962; 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Publications, 1976-1979; 1982-1985,; 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Quality in education, 1975-1978; includes position paper, "Degree granting abuses" (Box 4)
  - Regional chairs, See Regions: Council of Regional Chairs (Box 4)
  - Regions, See Regions: Committee (Box 4)
  - Relationships with other adult education associations, 1963-1966; includes "A paradigm for a new professional association for continuing higher education," a speech given by Alexander A. Liveright to the Association of University Evening Colleges, October 1964 (Box 4)
    See also Two-year institutions (Box 4); Interassociational relationships (Boxes 7, 8)
  - Research, 1952-1968; 1974-1979,; 1982-1984,; 1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Resolutions, 1969; 1984,; 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Resource linkages / Resource linkages and professional development, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Strategic planning, 1985-1988 (Box 4)
    See also Future (Box 3); Miscellaneous: Strategic planning retreat (Box 8)
  - Student personnel, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Student relations, 1983; 1984-1985,; 1988 (Box 4)
  - Teacher education through evening programs, 1963-1965 (Box 4)
  - Title I of higher education, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Time and site, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Two year institutions, 1979; 1988,; undated; includes report by the Committee on Relations on whether or not evening college deans of two-year colleges should be admitted to full membership in AUEC (Box 4)
  - Urban extension, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Ways and means, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Western regions (task force)
    See Regions: Western regions task force (Box 5)
- Regions
  - Constitutions and bylaws of regions (Box 4)
  - Council of regional chairs, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Guide for regional chairs, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Committee, 1964-1980; 1989; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Region I, 1964; 1967-1968,; 1977-1978,; 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    See also 1989 conferences: Regions I, II, III, IV (Toronto) (Box 5)
  - Region II, 1964-1965; 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - Region III, 1964-1968; 1970,; 1976-1978 (Box 4)
  - Region IV, 1963-1965; 1967-1968,; 1975-1979 (Box 4)
  - Region V, 1964-1968; 1974,; 1976-1978,; 1989 (Box 4)
  - Region VI, 1964-1965; 1968,; 1970,; 1977 (Box 4)
    See also 1989 conferences: Region VI (Purdue) (Box 5)
  - Region VII, 1964-1968; 1970,; 1975-1979,; 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    See also 1989 conferences: Region VII (Atlanta) (Box 5)
  - Region VIII, 1963-1967; 1972,; 1976,; 1978,; 1989 (Box 4)
    See also 1989 conferences: Region VIII (Indianola, Iowa) (Box 5)
  - Region IX, 1964-1967; 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    See also Western regions task force (Box 5)
  - Region X, 1964; 1967-1968,; 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Region XI, 1958; 1961,; 1964-1968,; 1989 (Box 5)
    See also 1989 conferences: Region XI (Vancouver) (Box 5)
  - Region XII, 1964; 1967 (Box 5)
  - Western regions task force, 1988-1989; concerned with increasing ACHE membership and activities in Regions IX and X (Box 5)
  - 1989 regional conferences
    - Regions I, II, III, IV (Toronto), 1989 (Box 5)
    - Region VI (Purdue), 1989 (Box 5)
    - Region VII (Atlanta), 1989 (Box 5)
    - Region VIII (Indianola, Iowa), 1989 (Box 5)
    - Region XI (Vancouver), 1989 (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  - 1961-1975, 15 folders (Box 5)
  - 1975-1981, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - 1986-1989, 1 folder (Box 6)
- Directories
  - 1962-1964, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - 1972-1976, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - 1979-1984, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - 1986 (Box 6)
  - 1988 (Box 6)
- Financial records
  - Financial reports, 1955-1985; 28 folders (Box 6)
  - Financial reports, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Income taxes, 1986 (Box 6)
- Institutional membership files
  - Membership reports and lists, 1988; undated (Box 6)
  - Adams State College, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Appalachian State University, 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - Arkansas State University, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - Auburn University (Auburn, Alabama), 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Auburn University (Montgomery, Alabama), 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Beaufort University, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Bentley College, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Bryan Community College, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Bloomfield College, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Brigham Young University, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Bronx Community College, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Chattanooga State Technical Community College, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Chestnut Hill College, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Chicago State College, 1967 (Box 6)
  - City University of New York, Graduate Center, 1974 (Box 6)
  - City University of New York, Herbert H. Lehman College, ca. 1970 (Box 6)
  - City University of New York, Queensborough Community College, 1967 (Box 6)
  - College of Charleston, 1974 (Box 6)
  - College of New Rochelle, 1978 (Box 6)
  - College of Notre Dame, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Dawson College, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Delaware Technical and Community College, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Delaware Valley College of Science and Agriculture, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Delgado Junior College, 1972-1972 (Box 6)
  - Dutchess Community College, 1967 (Box 6)
  - East Carolina University, 1969 (Box 6)
  - East Texas State University, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Eastern Michigan University, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Elmhurst College, 1966 (Box 7)
  - Emerson College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Fayetteville State University, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Florence-Darlington Technical College, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Florida Junior College at Jacksonville, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Franklin and Marshall College, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Frostburg State College, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Gannon College, 1979 (Box 7)
  - George Mason University, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Golden Gate University, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Grambling State University, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Guilford College, undated (ca.1970) (Box 7)
  - Gwynedd-Mercy College, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Indiana Central College, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Indiana State University, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Indiana University of Pennsylvania, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Loop College, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Malcolm X College, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Manhattan Community College, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Marietta College, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Marist College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Memphis State University, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Merrimack College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Miami Date Junior College, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Midlands Technical College, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Milwaukee Area Technical College, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Mississippi State College for Women, ca.1968 (Box 7)
  - Mohawk Valley Community College, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Montgomery College, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Monroe Community College, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Montclair State College, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Nassau Community College, 1967 (Box 7)
  - New Hampshire College, 1976 (Box 7)
  - New Haven College, 1967 (Box 7)
  - New York Institute of Technology, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Newark State College, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Northeastern Oklahoma State University, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Nova Scotia Technical College, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Onondaga Community College, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Orange County Community College, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Orangeburg-Calhoun Technical College, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Our Lady of Holy Cross College, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Philadelphia College of Textiles and Science, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Post College, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Quinnipiac College, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Rappahannock Community College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Regis College, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Richmond Professional Institution, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Roger Williams College, 1971-1973 (Box 7)
  - Rollins College, 1972 (Box 7)
  - St. Ambrose College, 1977 (Box 7)
  - St. Michael's College, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Salisbury State College, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Siena College, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Somerset County College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Southern Colorado State College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Southern Connecticut State College, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Southwest State College, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Springfield College, 1968 (Box 7)
  - State University College at Brockport, 1970 (Box 7)
  - State University College at Oswego, 1973 (Box 7)
  - State University College of Technology at Utica/Rome, 1978 (Box 7)
  - State University of New York at Albany, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - State University of New York at Stony Brook, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Tompkins County Community College, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Trenton State College, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Tri-State College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Troy State University, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Ulster County Community College, 1972 (Box 7)
  - University of Alabama at Birmingham, 1977 (Box 7)
  - University of Alabama at Huntsville, 1975 (Box 7)
  - University of Albuquerque, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - University of Arizona, 1975 (Box 7)
  - University of Colorado, 1963 (Box 7)
  - University of Georgia, 1970 (Box 7)
  - University of Houston, 1979 (Box 7)
  - University of Maine, 1963 (Box 7)
  - University of Massachusetts, 1972 (Box 7)
  - University of Missouri, 1969 (Box 7)
  - University of New Brunswick, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - University of New Hampshire, 1968 (Box 7)
  - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1967 (Box 7)
  - University of North Carolina at Charlotte, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
  - University of South Alabama, 1972 (Box 7)
  - University of South Carolina, 1978 (Box 7)
  - University of Tennessee at Martin, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - University of Tennessee at Nashville, 1973 (Box 7)
  - University of Virginia, 1966 (Box 7)
  - Ursinus College, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Ursuline College, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Wayne General and Technical College, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Western Carolina University, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Western New England College, 1966 (Box 7)
  - Worcester State College, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
- Interassociational relationships
  See also Committee files: Relationships with other adult education associations (Box 4)
  - Adult Education Association of the USA (AEA-USA), 1965-1969 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Sigma Lambda, 1975-1980; 1983 (Box 7)
  - American Assembly of Collegiate Schools of Business (AACSB), 1976-1978 (Box 7)
  - American Council on Education, 1964-1968; 1973,; 1977; following the correspondence (i.e. not intermingled by date) are a number of newsletters (Box 7)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO)
    - Articles of incorporation, bylaws, 1970; 1972 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1988 (Box 7)
    - Galaxy Conference, 1967 (Box 7)
      See also Miscellaneous: Galaxy Conference (Box 8)
    - International Associates Newsletter, 1983-1988 (Box 7)
    - International Associates Program of the International Council for Adult Education (ICAE), 1973; undated; program sponsored by CAEO (Box 7)
    - Leadership directories, 1977-1979; 1985-1988 (Box 7)
    - Membership lists, 1971 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1969-1988 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1969-1973; 1978-1979,; 1986-1987 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1970-1973; includes text of speech, "One Eye on the Future," K. Patricia Cross, Adult Educator of the Year; CAEO testimony before Senate Subcommittee on Education regarding S. 1814 (Box 7)
    - CAEO News, vol. 1 no. 2 and vol. 2 no. 1, 1974-1976 (Box 7)
    - Organizational profile, undated (Box 8)
    - Wingspread Conference, 1976 (Box 8)
  - Continuing Education Technical Assistance Center, 1979; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Council of National Organizations, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Evening Student Personnel Association, 1966; 1968-1969 (Box 8)
  - International Association of Evening Student Councils, 1963-1968 (Box 8)
  - International Council for Adult Education, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Library of Continuing Education, 1964; 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - National Education Association, 1968 (Box 8)
  - New York City Community College, 1971; includes report, "Five Years of Activity: A Summary Report," by the Division of Continuing Education and Extension Services (Box 8)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, Commission on Colleges, 1973; includes informational guide to the Continuing Education Unit (Box 8)
  - United States Association of Evening Students (USAES), 1973 (Box 8)
- Publications
  - Continuing Higher Education (journal)
    - Correspondence, 1976; 1978-1982 (Box 8)
    - Editor search, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Criteria and guidelines, 1988; 1992,; 1994 (Box 8)
  - Enrollment statistics, 1960-1965 (Box 8)
  - 5 Minutes with ACHE, 1977-1989; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - From the Dean's Desk..., 1964-1973; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Policies and practices, 1953; 1971,; 1982 (Box 8)
  - Principles of Good Practice, 1983; 1984 (Box 8)
  - Programs and registrations (AUEC), 1965-1973 (Box 8)
  - Programs and registrations (ACHE), 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Readings (on the Continuing Education Unit), 1972 (Box 9)
  - Regional News, 1975-1977 (Box 9)
  - Who's Who, 1964-1966 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Awards chronology, 2003; covers years 1965-2004; For 2004-2007, see CD-ROM in Committee files: Executive Committee, 2004-2007 (Box 3) (Box 9)
  - Brochures, 1976; 2000,; undated (Box 9)
  - Career education, 1976; includes "Proposed Responses by NUEA to Issues in Higher Education Amendments" and a lengthy report, "New Legislation for Career Education, enacted as Part C of Title III of the Education Amendments of 1976 (Public Law 94-482) (Box 9)
  - Canadian Association for University Continuing Education (CAUCE), 1988-1989; includes several annual reports and information on the 1989 annual conference (Box 9)
  - Chronology of officers and directors, 2004; covers years 1993-2004; For 2004-2007, see CD-ROM in Committee files: Executive Committee, 2004-2007 (Box 3) (Box 9)
  - Constitution and bylaws, 1967; 1977,; 1978,; 1980,; 1981,; 1983,; 1984,; 1986 (Box 9)
  - Galaxy Conference, 1967 (Box 9)
    See also Interassociational relationships: Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO): Galaxy Conference (Box 7)
  - Handbook of Working Rules, Policies and Procedures, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Historical statement and goals, 1988; 2000 (Box 9)
  - Leadership conference, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
  - Logo, 1978-1979; includes wide range of proposed designs, from classical to op art (Box 9)
  - Membership survey, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Organizational profile, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Strategic planning retreat, 1986; 2007; 2 folders; For 2007 strategic plan covering 2008-2010, see CD-ROM in Committee files: Executive Committee, 2004-2007 (Box 3) (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)